Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is פ"ד, Pey Dalet,
and we start at the top on the משנה. Mishnah. And we're
dealing with again eating the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, roasting, eating the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. The most recent discussion was what happens if
the meat is left over and it's נותר Nosar and what constitutes
that, the bones, bones with the marrow, the marrow is what dictates
the bones that have the marrow in them. And the various sinews,
we spoke about the גיד. Gid. I was corrected yesterday after the
end of שיעור Shiur that the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh is not
really a sinew, it's a nerve, a sciatic nerve, but it's, you
know, large enough and visible enough and חז"ל Chazal don't discriminate it
in terms of the language they use but obviously it is something
different. Yeah, the table shifted, if you want to separate them, be
my guest.
So, so, when they say the word גיד, Gid, you're saying it's
like a broad term that refers to either?
Yeah, so גיד Gid I think refers to like stringy things. Stringy
things. And whether that's a sinew or a, or a nerve, right,
you know, it's, I think it's an inclusive type of a term.
So we take a look now at the next משנה Mishnah that
continues in this discussion about what things are eaten, as we learned
yesterday, things that are considered meat and can be eaten are things
that if you don't eat are considered נותר Nosar and have to
be burned. So let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. כל
הנאכל בשור גדול, Kol hane’echal beshor gadol, any part of this animal
that if it were not a sheep or goat but if it
were a calf and were to then grow up and be a
cow, and that part would still be able to be eaten, so
יאכל בגדי הרך, Ye’achel begedi harach, that is eaten when it's a
tender young גדי הרך. Gedi Harach. So that's considered meat. Meaning so
presumably those things that—it's quite interesting—things that when the even if they're—it
seems the משנה Mishnah is saying that even things that are edible
now, if when the animal grows up they couldn't, they wouldn't be
eaten because they would harden,
or interestingly, somewhat strangely, even if it could be eaten in a
large goat, but if its counterpart would not be able to be
eaten in a large cow, somehow that's not considered meat, which is
quite a strange idea. I mean, presumably you wouldn't be יוצא Yotzei
your מצוה Mitzvah of קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Maybe you wouldn't have
to burn it if it's נותר. Nosar. So it seems like a
very formal type of a definition of what constitutes meat, even things
that are edible and so on. And then by saying the ראשי
כנפים
והסחוסים. Rashei knafayim vehasachchusim.
And included in this is the ראשי כנפים Rashei Knafayim and the
סחוסים. Sachchusim. So, how do they translate ראשי כנפים, Rashei Knafayim, does
anyone have an English there?
It’s a very interesting note here about forelegs. Forelegs, the tops of
the forelegs?
Yeah. And the סחוסים Sachchusim are what, the cartilage of the ear?
Right. Bristles, the bristles, cartilage of the ear. So, I’ll get to
the note in a minute, anyway, so these things, I don't know
what the, I don't know what's special about the tops of the
forelegs. רש"י Rashi says the same thing, שבראש גף הכתף, Sheberosh Gaf
HaKasef, but presumably it's some harder part of the animal. And the
cartilage of the ears is also, like, doesn't have too much meat
on them. And but presumably the point of the משנה Mishnah is
that those are included, which is strange. It's hard to see again,
would you really eat that from a grown cow? And we will
see a discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. What did you say, the
footnote you have there in the Artscroll says?
It’s something we’ve wrestled with for the past couple of days where
it talks about anything that hardens as an adult.
It says the skeleton of a young animal is composed largely of
cartilage, most of which later turns to bone. Thus there are many
parts of which could be eaten of an eight-day-old lamb or kid
that was offered, but nevertheless not count as portions as they tend
to harden with age. Maybe that's the concept of not breaking the
bone.
So that's interesting. Well, right, but it's, but here the concern is
not that you would be transgress breaking the bones but it constitutes
as meat. But that's an interesting point that I wasn't aware of,
that actually things convert, change into bone, that there are things that
start off as cartilage then become bone.
That's quite fascinating.
Yeah, that’s why even big things
almost can’t break, can’t break its arm almost. Uh-huh. First-born as in
a calf, it’s pliable. Interesting. Things would bend like a twig and
wouldn’t
break.
Oh, wow, that's fascinating. Instead of like a snap fracture. Just a
twig, it doesn’t really break, it just
bends over
like that, right.
Okay, so that's very interesting. So then what you actually do have
is, like I said, some formal definition of meat because in the
end it'll be bone. And again interesting, even if what's even stranger
is, even if it won't sort of transform significantly in this animal,
but if it would transform if we were dealing with a cow,
then it's not formally defined as meat and presumably you don't fulfill
your obligation, maybe also it's not a problem of נותר. Nosar. So,
yes.
Rabbi, I don’t understand the ratio here. I don’t understand the formal
definition of בשר Basar here. Why do you need the
phrase יאכל בגדי הרך? Ye'achel begedi harach? Why do you need that
phrase?
Because, because the פסח Pesach is a גדי הרך. Gedi Harach. It's
to point out the difference, that this is a young kid goat
or young lamb,
and much of it is edible, but that doesn't determine, the determinant
of whether it’s considered meat, again for the מצוה Mitzvah of פסח
Pesach and maybe for defining it as נותר Nosar if it's left
over, is whether its counterpart would be edible even in a large
cow. So which is something which is much...
which is so being defined in terms of a different animal at
a different age?
Right. If it were defined as its own animal when it grows
up, that that would be one thing. But anyway, so let's take
a look. No, no, it's fine. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. רבה רמי. Rabba Rami. רבה Rabba shows a contradiction. תנן,
Tnan, תנא משנה: Tna mishna: כל הנאכל בשור גדול יאכל בגדי הרך
ושאינו נאכל לא. Kol hane'echal beshor gadol ye'achel begdi harach veshe'eino ne'echal
lo. Presumably if it can't be eaten in a big ox, it's
not considered meat in a young kid goat. Is that really true?
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end of the משנה.
mishna. ראשי כנפיים והסחוסים, Rashei knafayim vehas'chusim,
somehow the tops of some of the shoulder blades and the cartilage
of the ear, the cartilage maybe in general, is considered meat. So
that doesn't fit the principle. והני לא מישתכלי בשור גדול, Vehani lo
mistachli beshor gadol, that can't be eaten in a big ox. So
I don't get it. The משנה, mishna, the first part doesn't fit
with the second part. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא תנאי, Ela Tannai, a thing, very sharp, a very surprising statement,
I mean we do have it sometimes, that the גמרא Gemara says
the two parts of the משנה mishna were pasted together. Remember, רבי'ס
Rebbi's job was editing the משנה mishna and that actually they represent
two different opinions of תנאים. Tannaim. והכי קתני, Vehachi katana, and now
we'll sort of try to smooth it over, but here's how you
have to essentially read the משנה. mishna.
כל הנאכל בשור גדול יאכל בגדי הרך ושאינו נאכל לא, Kol hane'echal
beshor gadol ye'achel begdi harach veshe'eino ne'echal lo, implicitly if it can't
be eaten in a big ox, it's not considered meat in the
goat, in the calf, in the sheep. ויש אומרים, Veyesh omrim, and
now introducing, however there are some that disagree and say אף ראשי
כנפיים והסחוסים, Af rashei knafayim vehas'chusim,
that there are things that even if they can't be eaten in
a large animal are considered meat in a small animal and maybe
there really are two different camps whether you look at it in
terms of what it is right now, whether you look at it
in terms of some objective, you know, measure and based on its
counterpart.
Is that a פירוש peirush or is that a נוסח? nusach?
No, it's a פירוש. peirush. It's really saying that you have two
different... right, no, it doesn't mean... yeah, even that is usually a
פירוש. peirush. But anyway, what it's really saying is that you have
two different opinions that are pasted together here. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
what?
Sorry, but the פסח pesach is meant for אכילה, achila, right? Right.
You'd think that you'd adopt the maximalist position, whatever can possibly be
eaten...
yeah, presumably... I understand, but they might be saying it says ואכלו
את הבשר בלילה הזה, Ve'achlu es habasar balaila hazeh, maybe it has
to be something that's defined as בשר, basar, okay? It's not just
something that's edible. So let's take a look.
But don't eat it... then again you're saying though the whole question
was the other thing, like the sinews, is that considered meat?
Yeah, so that's the question.
Yeah, רבא Rava is an interesting point. חסורי מחסרא, Chasurei mechsera, you
want to understand that it's a, you know, poor transmission
of the משנה, mishna, but what would be the point of writing
it intentionally this way?
Yeah, I mean, again, I think that what it's saying is in
sometimes, you know, the גמרא Gemara does take objection. How could you
say that you have two contradictory parts pasted together and so on.
It might be a feature of orality, in other words, that essentially...
Yeah, but I mean if
רבי, Rebbi, even if רבי Rebbi is collating different statements and a
כלל klal statement and then you have a particular statement and he's
putting it together, why would you put two opposing statements together without
ויש אומרים? veyesh omrim?
Or why would you leave out like, yeah, why would you leave
out the fact that they're not, that they don't actually work together?
Like is it really a little inattention that you're just pasting two
different things together? Yeah, I don't know. It's, I mean which is
why the גמרא Gemara generally resists it. רבא אמר מה קתני? Rava
amar mah katana? רבא Rava says, no, no, no, this actually is
explicating and it's all the same position. והכי קתני, Vehachi katana, this
is how to read it. כל הנאכל בשור גדול בשלקא, Kol hane'echal
beshor gadol beshalka, what you missed out is the context and it's
sort of like what sometimes the חסורי מחסרא chasurei mechsera is trying
to say the context. It means it could be eaten if it
was in a big ox if it was boiled, like double boiled,
which means that that will soften it. So the definition, although how
are you eating your פסח? pesach? You're roasting it. But again, remember,
what we're discussing right now is something that could, is edible as
it is right now. You're only trying to disqualify it by saying
in its counterpart in a large animal it's not edible and therefore
it shouldn't count as meat. Okay, but if you want to disqualify
based on an objective standard, what I'm going to tell you is,
as long as it could be edible in if it was boiled
and softened and so on, that's enough to constitute it as meat.
Now you're eating it roasted, but it is edible now the way
it is. You're trying to disqualify based on some other standard. Okay,
so as long as hypothetically it's edible in that other case, it's
also considered meat. כל הנאכל בשור גדול בשלקא, Kol hane'echal beshor gadol
beshalka, if it could be eaten in a large ox of this
part of the animal if it was like boiled, בשלקא beshalka is
like double boiled, like you know really softened, יאכל בגדי הרך בצלי,
ye'achel begdi harach betzli, then it could be eaten in a roasted
goat. So that's a very nice explanation. And that includes ומהן ראשי
כנפיים והסחוסים, u'mahen rashei knafayim vehas'chusim, and that would include these pieces
of the cartilage and so on. So that's nice. Now we're actually
saying is that if we want to disqualify something that right now
would totally be considered meat, it would have to be that even
in the most extreme case it would not be edible in a
large animal.
So then what would you be actually excluding?
I don't know. There's some parts that I'm sure even after you
boil them or whatnot, you know, really can't be eaten. I mean,
though you are right like, you know, if you think about, you
know, when you have like
a
chicken, a
whole... scratching yourself, you would eat them potentially. Okay, I don't know.
I don't know.
And so what's this really telling you? You couldn't figure it out
by just saying eat, you know, just eat whatever you can from
the goat?
No, it's but it's not saying that. You will find things that
are not edible even in if they're boiled if in a large
ox, and we'll see in a minute. And those things would be
excluded.
And they would be edible in a goat?
Yes. Yes. תניא כוותיה דרבא, Tanya Kevotei de-Rava, we taught like רבא.
Rava. כל הנאכל בשור גדול בשלקא יאכל בגדי הרך בצלי. Kol ha-ne'ekhal
be-shor gadol be-shalka ye'ekhal be-gedi ha-rakh be-tzali.
By the way, you know, it's questionable exactly what this ברייתא Beraita
is because שלקא shalka is Aramaic but the סף Saf בשלוק. beshaluk.
So anyway. ומאי הן, U-mai hein, and what are they? ראשי כנפיים
והסחוסים. Rats-kenafeim ve-ha-shakhusim. Other scholars have pointed out that very often you
get a תניא כוותיה Tanya Kevotei of an אמוראי Amoraic teaching in
the בבלי Bavli that's word-for-word what the אמורא Amora said, and that
the only attribution of this ברייתא Beraita is in the בבלי Bavli
in this context. It's in no other context. So you know, it
raises interesting questions because when the אמוראים Amoraim taught, they taught when
they gave their teachings as opposed to the back and forth of
the גמרא, Gemara, they gave it in the same משנה Mishneic עברי
Ivru
as the משנה. Mishna. We're often not aware of that because we're
so used to the Aramaic. But if you think about sort of
just when they give their rulings as opposed to the discussion, it's
in the same משנה Mishneic עברי. Ivru. So is it possible sometimes
that the בבלי Bavli might have had a transmission issue and some
things that maybe were, you know, were אמורא Amoraic statements got to
be understood also as ברייתא? Beraitas? It's an interesting phenomenon again that
sometimes you have a תניא כוותיה Tanya Kevotei of what an אמורא
Amora says which is word-for-word what the אמורא Amora says and appears
nowhere else. All right, anyway, let's take a look. וגידים הרכים, Ve-gidim
ha-rakhim, and now we get to something that might be—to now we
get to other particulars.
Soft sinews, which we said yesterday, which we said again today also
could include maybe nerves. Anyway, stringy things. נידונים כבשר, Nidunim ke-basar, also
count like meat. So of course now the question becomes, so what
are you excluding? So don't worry, we'll get to it. איתמר. Itmar.
Now we have another discussion which is going to seem to be
like exactly what we've been discussing until now, but איתמר Itmar means
it was taught elsewhere and this also is taught in חולין Chullin
if you look at the side for another discussion because the question
of what constitutes meat is not necessarily limited to קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, right? Other ramifications. What makes—what would cause טומאה Tum'ah if let's
say it was a dead animal, right? Or would it be considered
food in terms of whether it could—it could be susceptible to טומאה?
Tum'ah? So here's the discussion we have in חולין.
Chullin. איתמר Itmar doesn't always mean that it's someplace else also.
Or does it also mean... That's true.
But it's more like גופא gufa in a way.
No, איתמר Itmar is not גופא. gufa. איתמר Itmar does relate to
an independent discussion that's being placed here. Whether is it always referenced
elsewhere maybe not, but it doesn't mean that it's not—it still means
in the sense that we're to bring—bringing in from some other context
whether it's recorded or not.
Exactly. גידים שסופם
להקשות.
Gidim she-sofam le-hakshos. If you have these sinews that are in the
end going to get hard, which seems to be like exactly the
type of tissues that was going on in the משנה. Mishna. רבי
יוחנן אומר נמנים עליהם בפסח, Rabbi Yochanan omer nimnim aleihem be-pesach,
that you can be part—count as part of them for a קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. So they're considered meat, which again seems to be
exactly the point of our משנה. Mishna. ריש לקיש אומר אין נמנים
עליהם בפסח. Reish Lakish omer ein nimnim aleihem be-pesach. You can't. So
now we're not asking the question about will they be eaten by
an ox, but even in this animal itself, it's going to be
hard when the animal grows up. So it should be—that's—I mean the
question is what's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's position, right? Our משנה Mishna
seem—you know, our משנה Mishna seems to be that if it can't
be eaten when it grows up, then not. So let's take a
look.
What's this language נמנים עליהם? nimnim aleihem?
You can be part—you know, I—it's—it's an interesting point meaning the question
is like if it's another—you don't say
I want the rib steak and I want
the—Well you might if you only have a few pennies to contribute
and we feel bad for you and nobody else is having you
joining you to פסח, Pesach, fine. You can be part of our
group but you get to eat only the sinews. But
the הלכה halakhic relevance is the same, presumably. If I'm יוצא yotzei
the מצווה mitzvah of eating—of eating this counts as eating the meat,
then that can be my portion in the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
and I can chip in for that part of it. Why the
phrase it as one rather than the other? Presumably they're exactly determined
by the same question.
And it's better than
פסח Pesach because it's a bunch of people. This is my cut,
that's it.
See everybody, I paid for this lamb, I'm getting the steaks, you
get something else. Right. ורבי יוחנן Ve-Rabbi Yochanan
also—Okay, so this is the debate. So of course the משנה Mishna
sounds like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, if it can't be eaten when
it grows up. And this even when it grows up as a
sheep or goat, certainly it wouldn't count. Let's take a look.
ריש לקיש אומר אין נמנים עליהם. Reish Lakish omer ein nimnim aleihem.
רבי יוחנן נמנים עליהם. Rabbi Yochanan nimnim aleihem. בתר השתא אזלינן. Bat-hashta
azlinan.
You go by—yeah, exactly, it seems to be against the משנה, Mishna,
but it makes a lot of sense. You go by whether now
it's edible.
ריש לקיש אומר אין נמנים עליהם בפסח. Reish Lakish omer ein nimnim
aleihem be-pesach. ...at the end and that determines its identity because maybe
it's an objective definition of בשר. basar. איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן,
Eitivei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan, to Reish Lakish asked Rabbi Yochanan from
our משנה: Mishnah: כל הנאכל בשור גדול יאכל בגדי הרך. Kol ha-ne'echal
be-shor gadol ye'achel be-gadi ha-rach. מאי נינהו כנפיים והסחוסים? Mai ninhu knafayim
ve-ha-schusim?
So האני אין, hani in, these may be the case about this
cartilage, okay, but presumably because it is edible when the animal grows
up, but גידים שסופם להקשות, gidim she-sofam le-hakshot,
presumably if you have a sinew that's going to be hard and
won't be edible when it grows up, לא, lo,
you can't. אמר ליה, Amar lei, תנא האני והוא הדין להנך. Tanna
hani ve-hu ha-din le-hanach.
You know what? No, the hardened sinews is just like this cartilage
that's being referred to in the משנה Mishnah and that also in
theory can be eaten when it grows up. So it's quite funny
then they're not really debating do you go by now, do you
go by the future. What really Rabbi Yochanan is just saying is
even when it gets hard in the future, it will somewhat be
edible, which undercuts the whole strength of his position.
האני מאי טעמא? Hani mai ta'ama? One minute, why are those in
the משנה Mishnah considered to be acceptable? דמיתאכלי בשור גדול בשלוקא, De-mitachli
be-shor gadol be-shluka, because they can be eaten when the even in
an ox if you boil it. הכא נמי מיתאכלי בשור גדול בשלוקא.
Hacha nami mitachli be-shor gadol be-shluka. Here too by the sinews. So
again, it undercuts the whole debate. You know, on its face of
it, it was a very reasonable debate and Rabbi Yochanan's position would
probably be the much more persuasive one anyway, but you got the
problem of the משנה. Mishnah. So in the end, Rabbi Yochanan has
to agree in principle. In principle, I agree, it goes by whether
it will be edible when the animal grows up. I just am
having a more liberal definition of what I tend to believe falls
into that category of edible and let's also remember it means if
you boil it, etc., etc. So it then becomes a question.
You don't want to
be in this, yeah, you're going to get a really bad part
of פסח. Pesach. Right. אמר ליה רב ירמיה לרב אבין, Amar lei
Rav Yirmeya le-Rav Avin, so Rav Yirmeya said to Rav Avin, כי
אזלת לקמיה דרבי אבהו, ki azlat le-kamei de-Rabbi Abbahu, when you come
in front of Rabbi Abbahu, רמי ליה, rami lei, ask him the
following contradiction: מי אמר רבי יוחנן גידים שסופם להקשות נמנין עליהם בפסח?
Mi amar Rabbi Yochanan gidim she-sofam le-hakshot nimnin aleihem be-Pesach? Did Rabbi
Yochanan really say that this counts as meat and you could be
part of the, you could, that could be your portion, the
sinews? אלמא בתר השתא אזלינן. Alma batar hashta azlinan. It sounds again
taking it at face value, not the reconciled way, that you go
by its current status. והא רמי ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן, Ve-ha
rami lei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan, we know that Reish Lakish asked
from Rabbi Yochanan from a משנה Mishnah in חולין: Chullin: עור הראש
של עגל הרך מהו שייטמא? Or ha-rosh shel eigel ha-rach mahu she-yitamei?
Let's say you have the skin of the head of a nice
young calf.
What, can it become טמא? tamei? Now טמא tamei here is not
as נבילה. neveilah. The question here is as food, okay? Is it
considered edible and food to become טמא, tamei, to be susceptible to
טומאה? tumah? All right, is it something, you know, again, how many
people eat the head of an animal? והאמר ליה, Ve-ha amar lei,
it's also
not this, just the עור הראש, or ha-rosh, isn't that like?
I know, let's see, I understand, let's see what he says. ואמר
ליה, Ve-amar lei, right, it's not the meat, it's the skin.
ואמר ליה, Ve-amar lei, he said to him, אין מיטמא, ein mitamei,
it doesn't become טמא. tamei. So why not? Presumably if it's a
nice young goat, it is edible in the current state. אלמא בתר
בסוף אזלינן. Alma batar besof azlinan. You see for him when it
comes to טומאה, tumah, you don't just go by now, you say
in the end this is not edible. And if that's true by
טומאה, tumah, presumably, which by the way there the definition isn't even
meat, the definition is food, right? Food becomes טמא. tamei. So presumably
it's, you know, there is some objective standard that you have to
apply and presumably the same thing should apply here as well.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, so he
was asked to present this question to Rabbi Abbahu. So Rav Avin
said back to Rav Yirmeya... no, actually he did present the question.
A job like he did present the question. And then Rabbi Abbahu
said back to him, דרמא לך הא לא חש לקמחיה. De-rama lach
ha lo chash le-kimchei.
The one who who made this contradiction for you, you know, presumably
he was sending this message back to Rav Yirmeya or your Rebbe,
Rav Yirmeya, who said, oh, I've got this problem, ask Rabbi Abbahu
about it. He says he was not being careful with his wheat.
What does that mean? So Rashi has a great phrase. Rashi says
if you look at Rashi, לא חש לקמחיה, lo chash le-kimchei, explains
what this phrase means. Rashi says, למאי דהוא טחין עם חיטין סולת.
Le-mai de-hu tachin im chitin solet. He's not being he doesn't care
what he's grinding, whether he's grinding wheat or whether he's grinding
chaff, meaning you know because the whole idea by the way the
גמרא Gemara sometimes uses that sense about like to ask a question
is like to grind, you know. It speaks about you know דטחין,
de-tachin, right, and you have the wheat is when you have the
knowledge and right and טב ונקי tav ve-naki and then you actually
ask the question so you're grinding the wheat, you're analyzing it. So
there's, yeah, he's got these problems but he's not paying attention to
like you know how carefully he is with the material he's dealing
with. So he doesn't, you know, it's a silly question. Why is
it a silly question? לא חש לקמחיה. Lo chash le-kimchei. דהא רמי
ליה ריש
לקיש לרבי יוחנן. De-ha rami lei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan. Now
it's actually quite funny. It's not like it wasn't a good question,
but the point was you didn't pay attention to the end of
that סוגיא sugya because over there in חולין, Chullin, Reish Lakish asks
Rabbi Yochanan a contradiction about Rabbi Yochanan's position that this meat is
considered to be is not considered to be
food and
אמר ליה. amar lei. is a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. What does
it mean it's a דעת יחיד? da'as yachid? Because ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish made a contradiction to Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan from a משנה. mishna.
And the משנה... mishna... hold on let me just double check רש"י.
Rashi. One
minute.
Right, so basically the משנה, mishna, it's actually quite interesting. The משנה
mishna over there in חולין Chullin seems to support Rabbi יוחנן's Yochanan
position here. Seems to say in terms of the question of what
constitutes food and אוכל ochel for טומאה, tumah, you go by something's
current status. So over there in חולין Chullin what happened was is
that Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan was saying this skin of the head does
not constitute food or meat even though it's edible now. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says what do you do about this משנה mishna that
sounds like you do go by its current status? Again, almost reverse
than their position here. And Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan said back to him,
I don't hold of that משנה. mishna. That משנה mishna I believe
is a דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. And therefore I really hold of
the position that you don't go by the state of it now,
you go by what it's going to be in the future. Which
really means what? Which really means that he's saying that Rabbi יוחנן
Yochanan reversed his position. So it's funny, it's not like it wasn't
a good question. It actually was a great question. Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan
over there in חולין Chullin says you go by the future, here
he says you go by now. And his only answer was is
you know what you're right, it is a contradiction, it actually was
a contradiction also it seemed to contradict the משנה. mishna. And in
the end what Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan was saying was that he actually
abandoned his early position here, which is that you go by now,
and the implication of the משנה mishna over there in חולין Chullin
that you go by the now. And he wound up coming along,
coming around to the position of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish here and
says you go by the future. So at the end of the
day is that Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan basically reversed himself. Which is pretty
harsh then again to respond, oh what a stupid question. What a
stupid, it was a great question. Only point is that you didn't
know the end of the story. The end of the story is
that Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan reversed himself, which in the end works for
our משנה. mishna. Because the simple sense of our משנה mishna is
also you don't go by the now, you have to look at
what it's going to be in the future. Okay, so that's what
you have. Even though something is edible, it might not be considered
meat to be יוצא yotzei the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, maybe also
not for the question about burning it as נותר. nosar. It has
to go by some definition of the future, interestingly not only the
future of this animal but the future of what it would be
in a different animal. As long as, but if it's theoretically edible
in that context even by boiled, that works for now. Rabbi יוחנן
Yochanan who seemed to say that, reject the implications of this משנה,
mishna, you go by its current status now, the גמרא Gemara either
makes it like a technical question of what you think is theoretically
edible in the future or basically in the end winds up saying
that Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan reversed himself and winds up saying like our
משנה mishna implies that it does have to be edible in the
future as well. Yes.
Is this just a פסח Pesach issue? Like let's say I just
bring a regular קרבן, korban, I bring a שלמים, shelamim, you know,
then the, what's it? And I bring a younger one, do I
say oh well, you know, it's gonna be
older, it's gonna be נותר nosar if I don't eat it?
Right, it wouldn't be a נפקא מינה nafka mina for you יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of eating the meat, but about נותר. nosar.
In theory you're right, in theory we could, you know that's a
good point. And again the discussion does not direct, yesterday's discussion tied
it into נותר. nosar. Today's discussion did not. Is it theoretically possible
to say that it's enough meat to become נותר nosar but not
enough meat to be יוצא yotzei your חיוב chiyuv of פסח? Pesach?
And maybe there are different criteria. You know normally we don't assume
that but it is an interesting point if this discussion doesn't appear
by other קרבנות. korbanot. Now before we get on to the next
משנה, mishna, although you know what I'll just read the next משנה
mishna and use it as an opportunity to bring in the רמב"ם
Rambam I mentioned yesterday. So the משנה mishna says the following: השובר
את העצם בפסח הטהור. hashover et ha'etzem bePesach hatahor.
Now we're getting back to breaking bones which again was our focus
yesterday. So if you break, and we quoted this משנה mishna earlier,
if you break a bone in a כשר פסח kasher pesach or
טהור tahor פסח, Pesach הרי זה לוקה ארבעים, harei zeh lokeh arba'im,
you get your lashes. אבל המוותר בטהור, aval hamotir batahor,
but if you leave over the meat even though it's a כשר
פסח kasher pesach and it's a negative prohibition of leaving over the
meat but nevertheless it's a passive act that you're doing, there אינו
לוקה ארבעים. eino lokeh arba'im. There, and אינו לוקה ארבעים. eino lokeh
arba'im. There, והשובר בטמא, vehashover betamei, or if you break a bone
but it's not a כשר פסח, kasher Pesach it's a טמא tamei
פסח, Pesach, in those cases אינו לוקה ארבעים, eino lokeh arba'im, you
don't get lashes. One because you actually transgressed but it's not we
can't give you lashes for a technical reason and the other because
you didn't actually transgress the prohibition of breaking bones is only in
a כשר kasher פסח. Pesach So again we deal here with the
issue of breaking bones and this gets us to, allows me to
turn back to the רמב"ם Rambam I mentioned yesterday. So today since
you waited a day I actually xeroxed it.
And interestingly if you look at the top this is in פרק
י' הלכה י'. perek yud halacha yud. If you look at the
top הלכה י"א, halacha yud-aleph, but הלכה י' halacha yud is exactly,
actually exactly the משנה mishna we just read. Like גידים הרכים שסופן
להקשות gidim harakim shesofan lehakshot אף על פי שאינן ראויין לאכילה עתה
af al pi she'einan ra'uyin la'achila ata נאכלין בפסח ואין נמנין עליהם.
ne'echalin bePesach ve'ein nimnin aleihem.
So it's actually quite interesting by the way this gets to your
question, Dov, about נמנין עליהם. nimnin aleihem. It says נאכלין בפסח ne'echalin
bePesach ואין נמנין עליהם. ve'ein nimnin aleihem.
So the way the רמב"ם Rambam reads it, it actually reads our
משנה Mishna as well, which was not clear in our משנה, Mishna,
is that in theory you could be יוצא yotze if you eat
that meat because right now it's edible, but that can't be your
whole portion in the Pesach. Then you're not considered a partner in
the Pesach. Very interesting, a gap, and it goes to Michael's issue
as well about would it have implications of נותר nosar by other
קרבנות. korbanot. So the רמב"ם Rambam seems to say, again, this is
what bothered us, right? Which is, which is why is it not
meat if it's edible now? And the רמב"ם Rambam seems to say,
okay, it is meat and it will be נותר, nosar, it's just
a technical issue of is it enough significant enough that that should
be your portion in the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
But if I have a חצי זית chatzi zayit of this and
a חצי זית chatzi zayit of that, am I יוצא? yotze? I
don't know. Anyway, let's look at הלכה י"א. Halacha Yud-Alef. Anyway, that's
interesting number one, to limit the scope of what we were just
learning. Let's look now at הלכה י"א. Halacha Yud-Alef. כשאדם אוכל את
הפסח, Kesheadam ochel es haPesach,
when you're eating the Pesach, חותך הבשר ואוכל. chosech habasar ve'ochel. So,
there you are, you're eating, so you cut off a piece of
meat and you eat it. וחותך העצמות מן הפרק. vechosech ha'atzamos min
haperek. Now what do you do when you get to the bones?
So you cut them at the joint, you don't cut through the
bones, you cut them at the joint. ומפרקן אותן umefarkon osan and
if you want you can break, you can disconnect them at the
joint, that's not a bone. וכשהגיע לגיד הנשה, uchshehiga le'Gid HaNasheh,
then you get to the גיד, gid, okay? מוציאו, motzio,
take it out, ומניחו עם שאר הגידים, umeniacho im shear hagidim, put
it off to the side with the other, with the other גידים
gidim because again remember, גיד שסופו להקשות gid shesofo lehakshos or
whatever some of these גידים gidim you're not eating.
Wait, they cooked it with the גיד gid in it?
That's exactly what we're finding out. Okay, והעצמות, veha'atzamos, you put it
off to the side with the other things you're not going to
eat, the גידים gidim and the bones, והקרמות שיוצאים בשעת אכילה vehakromos
sheyotzim bishas achila and you know, the type of membranes that you
take out when you're eating them. שאין מנקרים אותו כשאר הבשר ואין
מחתכין אותו אלא צולין אותו שלם. she'ein menakrim oso kishar habasar ve'ein
mechat'chin oso ela tzolin oso shalem.
You do not do, you do not remove the גיד gid before
you roast it like other meat, and you don't chop it up,
but you do it whole and therefore you don't remove the גיד
gid beforehand. ואם חתכו חתיכות חתיכות כשר, ve'im chatcho chatichos chatichos kasher,
but by the way, if you did have it piecemeal and it
was not dismembered, it would be כשר, kasher והוא שלא יחסר איבר,
vehu shelo yecheisar eiver,
and that's as long as it's not missing any limb. That's a
discussion we had earlier about בדיעבד bedi'eved if it's not שלם, shalem,
it's all there but it's not in one piece. Okay, and then
he says: וצריך אדם להשמר שלא יניח מבשר הפסח עד הבוקר לא
יותיר ממנו עד בוקר. Vetzarich adam lehishamer shelo yanich mibasar haPesach ad
haboker lo yosir mimenu ad boker. Okay, so that's the issue of
נותר. nosar. Nice little summary of some of the issues we've been
talking about. But what we find out is the רמב"ם Rambam roasted
his קרבן פסח Korban Pesach with the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh in
it. Now there is a discussion in the גמרא Gemara whether יש
בגידים בנותן טעם, yesh begidim benosein ta'am, בדיעבד bedi'eved if you roast
something, cook something with a גיד, gid, does the גיד gid give
off taste, doesn't make the other meat problematic? Let's see what the
ראב"ד Ra'avad says. Okay, אמר אברהם, Amar Avraham, בחי ראשי אין איסור
גדול מזה. bechai roshi ein issur gadol mizeh. Okay,
in
if in my head, the life of my head, like in my,
in my God-given life, I've never seen any bigger prohibition משיצלה הפסח
עם גיד הנשה, misheyitzaleh haPesach im Gid HaNasheh, that
you should roast the Pesach with the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh in
it. ועם שמנו, ve'im shamno, and this is also yesterday's discussion remember
about the fat of the גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, which is technically
permissible but we have treated as forbidden. So that certainly gives off
taste and you're going to roast it with the fat? ועם תרבא
דתותי מאסנא, ve'im tarba d'susei masnei,
and the fat underneath the sides, right, which is another part in
the, in the animal which can't be eaten. ועם קרומות שבראש, ve'im
kromos shebarosh, and like the membranes in the head which also something
that shouldn't be eaten. And how could the רמב"ם Rambam not be
concerned about the טעם ta'am and about all these types of things?
ואם אזכה ואוכל מהפסח, ve'im ezkeh ve'ochal mehaPesach, if I ever merit
to eat the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, like I should live to
see משיח Mashiach and קרבן פסח Korban Pesach בפרט, bifrat, ויביאו לפני
כזה, veyaviu lefanay kizeh, someone
who would bring me a רמב"ם's Rambam Pesach, הייתי חובטו בקרקע לפניו,
hayisi chovto bakarka lefanav,
I'd throw it on the ground in his face.
He's quite emphatic about how dare anybody suggest this would be a
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. All right, so interesting to see, I mean
it's not fully for us right now, but to think about how
רמב"ם Rambam dealt with these issues. Some of these are only, you
know, might be only דרבנן d'rabbanan issues. Like the fat of the
גיד gid is not דאורייתא, d'oraisa, the גיד gid itself might not
give off a taste, and רמב"ם Rambam might have felt that those
are put aside for the sake of, you know, the מצוה mitzvah
of roasting it whole, even if interestingly בדיעבד bedi'eved you could be
יוצא yotze with doing it in another way. But the ראב"ד, Ra'avad,
of course, you know, takes great umbrage at that.
Meaning when you, you know, when you do it with all its
whatever it is, you know, the גידים וקרומות, gidim vekromos, and means
except for these parts which...
Yeah, you would roast... first take out the גיד. gid. Okay, let's
take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. I'll tell you. Let's
take a look. He didn't say 'I throw it in his face',
I throw
it לפניו. lefanav. Not בפניו. befanav. Okay, okay. בשלמא, Bishlama, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא, Bishlama, of course if somebody brought
him that Pesach he wouldn't have been נמנה nimna על האחסו, al
ha-achsu, so you know... okay anyway. בשלמא מותיר Bishlama moseir says the
גמרא. Gemara. I understand the case of leaving over בטהור betahor in
a כשר kasher Pesach that you don't get lashes.
דתניא, Detanya, לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש
תשרופו. Lo sosiru mimenu ad boker vehanosar mimenu ad boker ba'esh tisrofu.
בא הכתוב ליתן עשה אחר לא תעשה, Ba haksav litein asei achar
lo sa'asei, gives a positive מצוה mitzvah after the negative one, לומר
שאין לוקין, lomar she'ein lokin, that you don't get lashes, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי
Rebbi, יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says because it says Michael said ניתק לעשה
*nitak l'asei* connected to an עשה *asei*. רבי Rebbi, יעקב אומר לא
lo, מן השם *Rabbi Yaakov omer lo minahashem* that you don't need
that reason, אלא ela, משום דהוה ליה לאו שאין בו מעשה *ela
mishum d'havei lei lav she'ein bo ma'aseh* it's passive, דאין לוקין עליו
*d'ein lokin alei* and you don't get lashes. Now I would say
interestingly, Rashi says what is the reason for it to be exempt
by ניתק לעשה *nitak l'asei*? So Rashi says two explanations. One is
that the עשה *asei* somehow is a תיקון *tikkun* of the
transgression, so therefore it somewhat mitigates the severity of it because you
do the עשה *asei* to somehow fix it. It won't totally fix
the fact that it was left over, but you burn it, whatever,
it's somewhat of a corrective. And the other reason Rashi says is
the technical reason, that the Torah tells us לא תחסום שור בדישו
*lo sachsom shor b'disho*, don't muzzle an ox, and then right afterwards
it speaks about lashes, so it has to be similar to that
prohibition of muzzling an ox, and this technically isn't similar because this
is not just a לא תעשה *lo sa'asei*, it's a לא תעשה
*lo sa'asei* with an עשה *asei* connected. So it is interesting, the
only reason I bring it up is obviously the first one is
a more satisfying explanation, but that Rashi is sort of positing there's
two ways of understanding these exceptions, which is often an interesting question
about parameters and exceptions and so on. Is it a formal technical
reason? There's just formal rules, not everything gets in the category, or
is there like a logic behind this, that it's not so bad
if you're only passive? It's not so bad
if you've done something to correct it. Obviously there's probably an interaction
between the two. Meaning you wouldn't have a completely arbitrary formal rule.
You don't say, well, it has to be like muzzling an ox
so you only get lashes for prohibitions that relate to animals or
prohibitions that relate to muzzles. If you're going to identify characteristics that
you're saying it has to be like this, it's going to be
salient, relevant characteristics that make sense why it should be more severe
than another type of a case. Nevertheless, once you define the category,
you might put things in the category that don't exactly have the
same dictated logic, but once you've defined the category based on that
logic, then it becomes a formal category. So there's usually an interplay
between those two. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says I get why
you don't get lashes for נותר notar. *nosar*. אלא Ella, *ella*, but
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
אלא Ella, שובר בטמא מנלן *ella shover b'tamei minalan*? How about breaking
a bone with a טמא tamei. *tamei* פסח Pesach, *Pesach*? We discussed
this already a day or two ago, but now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is discussing it again. Where do you know you don't get
lashes? You broke a bone of the פסח Pesach, *Pesach*? דאמר קרא
*de'amar kra*, the פסוק *pasuk* says, ועצם לא תשברו בו ve'etzem lo
tishberu vo *v'etzem lo sishberu bo*. Don't break a bone in it.
So what's the extra word בו *bo*? בו בכשר ולא בפסול *bo
b'kasher v'lo b'pasul*, that only if it's a כשר kasher *kasher* פסח
Pesach. *Pesach* do you transgress, not if it is a not kosher
one. תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*. Now we're going to look more at
this. ועצם לא תשברו בו ve'etzem lo tishberu vo, *v'etzem lo sishberu
bo*, בו בכשר ולא בפסול *bo b'kasher v'lo b'pasul*. רבי אומר Rabbi
omer *Rebbi omer*, בבית אחד יאכל be'bayis echad yeachel ועצם לא תשברו
בו *b'vayis echad ye'achel v'etzem lo sishberu bo*. So he says it
connects it to eating also the prohibition of breaking a bone, so
it's not an emphasis on the technical word בו *bo* but on
the connection of eating. כל הראוי לאכילה יש בו משום שבירת עצם
yesh bo mishum sheviras etzem ושאין ראוי לאכילה raoy leachila, אין בו
משום שבירת עצם ein bo mishum shevirat etzem. *kol hara'ui l'achila yesh
bo mishum shviras etzem, v'she'ein ra'ui l'achila ein bo mishum shviras etzem*.
It has to be fit to be eaten. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say fit to be eaten and פסול pasul,
*pasul* seem to be essentially the same thing. מאי בינייהו *mai beinaihu*?
What's the difference between רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* and the תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma*? אמר רב אמי פסח pesach הבא בטומאה איכא בינייהו *amar Rav
Ami Pesach ha'ba b'tumah ika beinaihu*. Let's say there was a פסח
pesach, *Pesach* that was brought בציבור בטומאה *b'tzibur b'tumah*. למאן דאמר כשר
kasher, *l'man d'amar kasher*,
according to the one that says כשר kasher *kasher*, האי פסול pasul,
*hai pasul*. Technically it's a פסול pasul *pasul* פסח pesach *Pesach* that
you're allowed to eat.
Rashi says again reflecting the idea that טומאה *tumah* is דחויה בציבור
*dechuya b'tzibur* not הותרה *hutra*, so it still has the sense of
being טמא tamei, *tamei* and problematic,
but you're permitted to eat it.
And so then in that case what,
you can't, you would not transgress the prohibition of breaking bones because
it's technically
the nature of the פסח Pesach *Pesach* as a קרבן korban *korban*
is that it is a פסול pasul, *pasul* קרבן korban. *korban* which
you just are allowed to eat. למאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה leman d'amar
raoy leachila, *l'man d'amar ra'ui l'achila*, however if you say whether it's
fit to be eaten, that raises a question of technically can it
be eaten? האי נמי ראוי לאכילה ra'uy l'achilah *hai nami ra'ui l'achila*.
So that would be a difference between רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*. רבי Rebbi
*Rebbi* would say the prohibition applies in that case and the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* would say it does not. רב יוסף אמר *Rav
Yosef amar* no, כי האי גוונא דכולי עלמא אין בו משום שבירת
עצם ein bo mishum shvirat etzem, *ki hai gavna d'chulei alma ein
bo mishum shviras etzem*. I'm sorry. It's interesting because if you would
have asked me, I would have said in that case everybody says
יש בו משום שבירת עצם yesh bo mishum sheviras etzem, *yesh bo
mishum shviras etzem*, once you're allowed to eat it, you should have
the prohibition. Interestingly רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* goes the opposite direction. If
technically it's טמא *tamei*, even if you're allowed to eat it, everybody
says you don't transgress. Now some take out the next line, but
the line we have in our גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is דרבי לאקולי
קאתא *d'Rebbi l'akulei ka'asei*. He's arguing that רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* is not
just an independent definition, which sometimes could be a חומרא *chumra*, sometimes
a קולא kula *kula*. רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*'s whole point is to be
more lenient, not to be more strict or not to be independent.
So therefore here, we're not going to use רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*'s position
to say you do transgress. רבי Rabbi *Rebbi*'s only trying to be
more lenient. Since it's פסול pasul. *pasul* and it's טמא *tamei*, everybody
would say you don't transgress. והאי הא פסול pasul, הוא *v'hai ha
pasul hu*, רבי Rabbi *Rebbi* would agree to the idea that once
it's פסול pasul *pasul* you don't transgress. He just wants to get
you off in other cases. So what are the other cases? אלא
הייתה לו שעת הכושר ונפסל איכא בינייהו *ella haysa lo sha'as kosher
v'nifsal ika beinaihu*, like we saw the other day. If it was
once כשר kasher *kasher* and now it's פסול pasul. *pasul*. It was
okay and now it became טמא *tamei*. למאן דאמר כשר kasher. *l'man
d'amar kasher*, the one that says that it's about... status is a
כשר kasher. פסח, הי כשר הוא, hai kasher hu, then it is
כשר kasher because once it was כשר. kasher, למאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה,
leman d'amar raoy leachila,
if you say however no, you only transgress if it's fit to
be eaten, הא השתא לאו ראוי לאכילה הוא, ha hashtaa lav raoy
leachila hu, right now it can't be eaten. If you say was
the קרבן כשר, korban kasher, the קרבן korban was כשר. kasher If
you say can it be eaten, right now it can't be eaten,
right now it is טמא. So Rebbi would be more lenient therefore
and get you off from that case because right now it can't
be eaten. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, Abaye says, כולי עלמא כהאי גוונא
אין בו משום שבירת עצם. kulei alma kihai gavna ein bo mishum
shevirat etzem. I gotta tell you, this is going to be the
structure of the whole דף. daf. Every אמורא Amora is going to
suggest a way of understanding the מחלוקת, machlokes, and the next אמורא
Amora is going to say, no, in that case everybody agrees. Of
course, which way they agree will be up to the אמורא Amora
to say. Okay, so Abaye says in that case everybody would say
that you do not transgress if right now it can’t be eaten
and right now it’s פסול, pasul, even if it was כשר kasher,
in the past.
מאי טעמא? mai taama? השתא מיהא פסול הוא. hashtaa miha pasul hu.
Right now it’s פסול, pasul. everybody would say that’s enough to get
you off. אלא שבירת עצם מבעוד יום איבעי לן. ella sheviras etzem
mibod yom itbeinan. Now this is interesting. What about if you broke
a bone on the 14th before it was nightfall? Okay, it’s a
totally כשר kasher פסח but it’s not yet the time to eat
it. למאן דאמר כשר הא כשר. leman d'amar kasher ha kasher. You’ve
broken it already. Yes, there was a slaughter on the 14th like
every קרבן פסח, korban pesach, and you go ahead and before nightfall
you break a bone. Okay, so it’s totally a כשר kasher פסח
but it’s not yet the time of eating it.
לאו ראוי לאכילה
בזמן.
lav raoy
leachila bazman.
Exactly. So if it’s כשר, kasher. so it’s כשר kasher. and you
transgress. למאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה, L'man d'amar ra'uy l'achilah, according to Rebbi,
ראוי לאכילה, ra'uy l'achilah השתא לאו בר אכילה הוא, hashtaa lav bar
achila hu, it’s not fit to be eaten yet and therefore you
get off according to Rebbi. Okay. מתיבי, meitivei, they asked on this,
רבי אומר נמנין על המוח שבראש ואין נמנין על המוח שבקולית. Rebbi
omer nimniin al hamoach shebarosh ve-ein nimniin al hamoach shebekullis. You can
become—you can have again, you’re part of the פסח can be the
מוח שבראש. moach shebarosh. Okay, you give your five bucks for the
פסח, we’ll give you the מוח שבראש. moach shebarosh. That is extractable.
Why is that extractable? You go through the nasal cavity. But you
cannot be
the—get—have your portion of the פסח be the marrow in the קולית,
kullis, I think that’s the thigh bone. What do they say there?
Thigh bone? Okay. Even though there’s a lot of marrow there. Why
not? Because there’s no way to get to it. מוח שבראש. moach
shebarosh. So the גמרא Gemara says now, let’s understand this. מוח שבראש
מאי טעמא? moach shebarosh mai taama? Why can you have a portion
in the marrow in the head? הואיל ויכול לגררו ולהוציאו. hoil veyachol
legorero ulehotzi-o. Because you can scrape it out through the nasal cavity.
Literally. Right, probably means the brain. You’re right.
It probably means the brain. מוח. moach. Yeah, literally מוח. moach. ואי
סלקא דעתך שבירת עצם מבעוד יום שפיר דמי. ve-isalkadateich shevirat etzem mibod
yom find shapira dami. But if Rebbi, who is the author of
this teaching himself, were to hold you could break the bones on
the 14th without transgressing, so then you could get the marrow from
all parts of the animal. קולית נמי. kullis nami. So by the
thigh bone as
well. נתבריה מבעוד יום nitberennu mibod yom and get out the marrow,
ונמני עליה, venimni aleih, and why can’t that be your portion? So
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so Abaye would say back to
you, ולטעמך, uletaimaich, and according to your reasoning, your assumption is like
we’ve always been assuming that you can’t break it the day before,
and then you would have been okay with the idea that you
can’t have the marrow. Why? I’ll tell you how you can get
the marrow out of this thigh bone according to everyone.
מחשכה נמי. mechashcheicha nami. Even after it gets dark, נייתי גומרא, neisei
gumreta, why not take a coal, a hot coal, וניחוש
עליה, venichos aleih, and put the bone on it, וניקלה, venikla, and
let it burn a piece of the bone because it’s only a
prohibition to break it, not to burn it. Okay, also it’s a
little bit of גרמא, grama, you’re not doing it directly, but the
פשט pshat also is that it’s being burned, not being cracked and
broken. ונפקה למוח דידיה, venappekei lemoach dideih, and then you could get
out the marrow. ונמני עליה, venimni aleih, and why and that could
be your
portion? דהתניא, dehatanya, for we have a ברייתא braita that
says: אבל השורף עצמות aval hasoreif atzamot והמחתך בגידין, vehamekhattaich begiddin, obviously,
אין בו משום שבירת עצם. ein bo mishum sheviras etzem The second
part is obvious, that’s the רמב"ם Rambam about cutting it at the
joint. But if you burn the bones, you don’t transgress. So anyway
you got a question: why can’t you have a portion of the
marrow? אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ella mai itlach lemeimar, what would
your response be to that question?
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, so there’s a debate of why how we
why it is that you can’t get that you can’t be part
of the marrow in a bone even though there’s a way of
getting it out. אביי אמר משום פק פקא. Abaye amar mishum pak
paka. We’re afraid that in the process of burning the bone it’s
going to cause other parts of the bone to crack. Okay, you
apply the heat to it, part will burn, part will crack. And
again, it’s interesting, you’ll probably transgress by גרמא, grama, not directly, but
nevertheless, okay, you are breaking a bone, even if it is only
by גרמא. grama. And therefore we don’t want to let you do
it. רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says
in that case everybody would agree
then—well, in theory you could do it, but we don’t want to
let you do it.
But wait, Rebbi would say that would be a case of שבירת
עצם, shevirat etzem, right?
Yeah, but we’re talking—we haven’t got up to the case of the
14th yet. רבא אמר משום הפסד קדשים. Rava amar mishum hefsed kodashim.
Rava says I’m afraid that if you burn it, you’re going to
destroy a part of a קרבן. korban Which part? דקמפסיד ליה בידיים.
dekamapsid lei beyadayim. You’re directly destroying—now big deal, you’re destroying a bone,
but you’re also directly burning some of the marrow. marrow inside. And
of course that marrow, if you don't burn the bone, is going
to become פסול pasul, anyway, it's going to be נותר. But better
let that happen passively than actively destroy part of the קרבן korban
that could in theory be eaten. דילמא אכלה נורא ממאי דאי, dilma
achla nora mimai de'i, maybe the fire will burn some of the
marrow מבעוד יום? mibod yom? That's why, you know, even though technically
you could, we're not going to let you do everything you technically
could because there'll be problems. So, you wanted to say according to
רבי, Rabbi how about the fact that you could break the bone
on the day before and why therefore can't you be part of
marrow? I'll give you another re... technically you're right, but there's a
practical issue. Right, technically you could, but you really think we're going
to let you break bones of a פסח on the fourteenth even
if you don't transgress? That's bad business. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so מבעוד יום נמי mibod yom nami on the fourteenth as well
according to רבי, Rabbi's גזירה מבעוד יום אטו משחשיכה. gezeira mibod yom
atu mishe'chashecha. We're not going to let people break bones, start breaking
bones, scraping out the marrow, because they'll wind up doing it after
the at nightfall as well. So technically you're right, but the rabbis
aren't going to let you do it and therefore once the once
you're not allowed to do it, you can that cannot be your
part of the קרבן פסח.
korban Pesach. We're optimistic that people can do תשובה teshuva but we're
not optimistic that they won't refrain from breaking the bones after the
sunset.
Yeah, there's a good דרוש drush in that. Okay.
רב פפא אמר Rav Pappa amar but didn't he just say that
the מחלוקת machlokes is שבירת עצם מבעוד יום? shvirat etzem mibod yom?
Right. But didn't we just say that he doesn't even רבי Rabbi
would say that he doesn't want you to do it because right
דרבנן.
derabanan. But דאורייתא de'oraisa you don't transgress. So now we're saying according
to רבי the difference is אכלת פסח מבעוד יום achalat Pesach mibod
yom which is not yet the time of eating. According to רבי
biblically you wouldn't transgress, rabbinically we won't let you do it, but
biblically you won't transgress. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, רב פפא
Rav Pappa says כי האי גוונא כולי עלמא יש בו משום שבירת
עצם, ki hai gavna kulei alma yesh bo mishum shvirat etzem,
which is what I think we would have assumed. In that case,
even רבי would say that you transgress, even though it's not yet
the time. מאי טעמא לאורו סמכיה לאכילה. mai ta'ama le'oro samchei l'achila.
It's going to be fit to be eaten, it's on the path
of being eaten, so therefore even רבי would say you transgress on
the fourteenth. אלא באבר שיצא מקצתו קמיפלגי. ela be'eiver sheyatza miktzato kamiflagi.
The case is a little a half of the arm was went
outside of the wall of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And when something goes out
of its boundaries, whether it can only be eaten in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and goes out of the עזרה, Azara, where it
only in ירושלים Yerushalayim and goes out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, then it
becomes פסול, pasul it's a פסול יוצא, psul yotzei, it left its
proper boundaries. So מאן דאמר כשר, man de'amar kasher, the one that
says it's כשר, kasher, הכשר הוא. hakasher hu. So okay, the remainder
of the of the limb is כשר kasher. and you can't break
it because part of it is כשר kasher, even though half of
it is פסול. ומאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה, uman de'amar ra'ui l'achila, but
the one that says fit to be eaten, האי לאו בר אכילה
הוא, hai lav bar achila hu, it can't be eaten. Now תוספות
Tosafot says what do you mean? It can be eaten. The same
thing about the כשר. kasher. Half of it is פסול, half is
כשר. kasher Half can be eaten, half can't be eaten. Right? It's
not clear exactly why this should make why this should make no
he's talking
about breaking the part that went outside, right?
I know, but as רש"י Rashi points out, if you break the
bone you're breaking it's you've got a limb, right, and this part
has gone outside and this part has not, and you break the
bone here, the good
part is still broken.
You're breaking half of the from this part of the thing you're
breaking a bone of a פסול but from this you're breaking a
bone of a כשר, kasher, right?
It's not clear like a you know
like no we're not talking we're not talking about that case. That's
why we talked about half the limb to make it an interesting
case. Okay. So anyway, תוספות Tosafot says it's not exactly clear why
we're willing to say, oh, from the אכילה achila perspective it's not
fit to be eaten. Like if from one of them we look
from the perspective of the good part, why on the other do
we only look from the perspective of the bad part? So it's
not exactly clear. Anyway, moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
דתניא, detanya, like we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי ישמעאל בנו
של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, Rebbi Yishmael beno shel Rebbi Yochanan
ben Beroka omer, אבר שיצא מקצתו, eiver sheyatza miktzato, half the limb
went out, ושברו, veshavro, and you broke it at the place where,
you know, the the line that it crossed, אין בו משום שבירת
עצם, ein bo mishum sheviras etzem you don't transgress because at least
the half of the of the bone being broken is פסול. Okay.
רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר כולי עלמא אין בו משום שבירת
עצם, Rav Sheshet brei de'Rav Idi amar kulei alma ein bo mishum
shvirat etzem, since I guess we have a ברייתא braita that says
it anyway. Everybody would say you don't transgress. Again, interestingly, even though
half of it is totally כשר. kasher, דהאי אבר הפסול הוא, de'hai
eiver hapasul hu, that limb is פסול, or at least half of
it is פסול. And again the assumption okay, fine.
Fine. אלא, so what is the case that they debate? שבירת עצם
בנא איכא בינייהו. shvirat etzem bena ika beina'ihu. The animal has not
yet been roasted. It's raw. Okay. It's sort of similar to the
idea of the fourteenth. It's a totally fine animal, animal, it's just
not yet in the stage where it can be eaten.
No, but one is external and one is internal to use that
same dichotomy. That's the way what's going on.
Right. Although personally I would think that if it's on the fifteenth
already and it's the time of eating, you know, that that should
more dictate, but you're right, you know, he's presumably assuming, no, if
it's actually in a state that it's fit to be, that's not
fit, that's something about the very identity of the thing itself.
מאן דאמר כשר הכשר הוא, man de'amar kasher hakesher hu, it's about
being כשר, kasher. it's כשר. kasher Okay, it's a כשר פסח and
you would transgress. מאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה man de'amar ra'ui l'achila again
assuming that רבי is coming to be lenient and about being fit
to be eaten like if to be eaten as an additional exemption,
not the only but the additional exemption, השתא אינו ראוי לאכילה hashta
eino ra'uy l'achilah right now in its current physical state it's not
fit to be eaten.
Even so, you couldn't break the bones anyway, right?
Yeah, right, we're talking about דאורייתא. d'Oraita. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar כגון דא יש בה משום שבירת העצם
k'gaon da yesh bah mishum shevirat ha-etzem similar to what the גמרא
Gemara's said about the fourteenth, give me a break, everybody would say
you transgress. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? דחזי לאכילה, De-chazi
l'achilah, it's it can be eaten as long as you just roast
it. דמטו ליה ואכיל ליה, Dematu lei ve-achil lei, you roast it
and eat it. אלא, it's so interesting how easily this גמרא reads,
you know, it's... אלא, there's no real discussion, it's just different scenarios.
אלא שבירת האליה איכא בינייהו, Ella shevirat ha-alyah ika beina'iyhu, the difference
is breaking the fat tail. Now I have to admit that I
did not get a chance to check it up, but Dov as
you're here you could look on Wikipedia, but my assumption was was
that there wasn't bones in the fat tail. A sheep has a
huge fat tail. Dov is going to check in the back, right?
What? Of course if it had no bones, what would support it?
But anyway, the גמרא is but the fat tail was something that
gets burned on the altar and the גמרא here, which knew its
animals and its agriculture much better than I do, assumes that there
is some bone to be broken. Okay. למאן דאמר כשר הכשר הוא,
L'man d'amar kasher ha-kasher hu, if it's a כשר so then you're
breaking a bone of a part of the כשר קרבן. kasher korban.
The fat part does go on... it gets burned, okay, but it's
still כשר, it's part of a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. למאן דאמר
ראוי לאכילה, L'man d'amar ra'uy l'achilah, if it's about being fit to
be eaten, האי אינו ראוי לאכילה, hai eino ra'uy l'achilah, it's not
part of the animal that's being eaten. Did you find anything?
Oxtails are bony, gelatin-rich meat.
Bony, oxtails... but is that... but how about sheep tails, that's what
they call a fat tail?
No, no,
no, it's a sheep, sheep have this huge fat tail around their
tush or whatever, like circles around, and that's why it's all about...
it's all fat.
But we go by the...
oh, I don't know about... anyway, tell me what you find, but
that's... anyway, okay, that's in the other direction. No, is it? Anyway...
so that's an interesting
point, but for שבירת עצם, shevirat etzem, if now it's not an
עצם... etzem... tell me what you find about
the anatomy, totally, totally.
Okay, so האי
אינו ראוי לאכילה דאליה לגבוה סלקא. hai eino ra'uy l'achilah d'alyah l'gavoha
salka. Okay, so that makes sense. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi amar
כל האי כגון דא ודאי... kol hai k'gaon da vadai... here we
have the word ודאי vadai which we didn't have before. What type
of poor question is that?
Everybody would say ודאי אין בה משום שבירת העצם vadai ein bah
mishum shevirat ha-etzem דודאי אינה ראויה לאכילה כלל. d'vadai einah ra'uyah l'achilah
klal. Even the חכמים Chachamim that speak about פסול, they might not
have a ראוי לאכילה rauy l'achilah category, but at least they mean
meat, at least they mean the part of the animal that is...
it's worth talking about eating. Okay, not this. אלא אבר שאין עליו
כזית בשר איכא בינייהו. Ella evar she-ein alav k'zayit basar ika beina'iyhu.
Now this is very interesting. This, I think, would never have occurred
to me that this might be an exception. Let's say you have
a limb that is stripped of the meat and doesn't even have
a כזית kzayit of meat on it right now. It's just the
bone by itself without any surrounding meat. למאן דאמר כשר האי כשר
הוא, L'man d'amar kasher hai kasher hu, if you say כשר, okay,
it's part of a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. למאן דאמר ראוי לאכילה,
L'man d'amar ra'uy l'achilah... it's not a definition of the קרבן in
totality, it's a definition of the thing right in front of you
that you're holding onto. בעינן שיעור אכילה וליכא, be'inan shiur achilah ve-leika,
you need in the limb in front of you that you're breaking
the bone of an amount that can be eaten, you need a
כזית. kzayit. So the big חידוש chiddush here is that you define
ראוי לאכילה not by the קרבן as a whole, but by the
limb that you actually are holding onto.
But if it doesn't have a כזית, kzayit, it's going to be
a מום, mum, like what...
no, no, no, no, I assume it means that you stripped it,
you already ate the meat off of it and then you're breaking
the bone. Not that it naturally was that way. Currently, the way
it is right now in front of you. Yeah, that of course,
the normal way is you eat all the meat and then you
start chomping the bones.
Oh, I always assumed though you ate your קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
right? אסור לשבור... assur lishbor... yeah,
yeah, I understand.
I do not think they're saying that naturally it...
no. Yeah, and so...
so let's keep on going.
So then you can't like chop it before eating the meat. Sure.
Yeah, as you're eating it and as there's meat on it. But
if you actually ate off all the meat... רבינא אמר Ravina amar
כגון דא לית בה משום שבירת עצם. k'gaon da leit bah mishum
shevirat etzem. Look at this, you know, again to me it's like
a shock that that would be exempt, but he says no, everybody
would say you're exempt, דבעינן שיעור אכילה, d'be'inan shiur achilah,
you need there to be meat on the bones, you need there
to be an edible amount. אלא אבר... Ella evar... anything, Dov, about
the fat tail of sheep?
Not directly, but one second.
Okay, אבר שיש בו מוח מבפנים...
evar she-yesh
bo moach mi-bifnim... what? Bone marrow inside which is a כזית. kzayit.
All right, well we'll get to that. That would also count, but
there has to be... it wouldn't be כזית kzayit necessarily there. There
has to be a כזית kzayit on or in the bone. אלא
אבר שאין עליו כזית בשר במקום זה ויש בו כזית בשר במקום
אחר איכא בינייהו. Ella evar she-ein alav k'zayit basar be-makom zeh ve-yesh
bo k'zayit basar be-makom acher ika beina'iyhu.
What if there's not a כזית kzayit of meat at the place
where you are breaking it? Again, this is like shocking. There's a
כזית kzayit of meat like lower on, you know, in the limb,
but the place you're breaking it does not have any meat on
it, or not enough meat on it. למאן דאמר כשר האי כשר
הוא, L'man d'amar kasher hai kasher hu, it's כשר. למאן דאמר ראוי
לאכילה... be eating and it needs to be fit for eating, בעינן
bainan שיעור אכילה במקום שבירה, shiur achilah bemakom shevirah, you need there
to be a כזית kzayis at the place where it's being broken,
והא ליכא veha lekka and you don't have that. Now that already
you could say maybe is what you're saying that it naturally didn't
have that much meat at parts of the bones which don't, parts
of the animal which
don't naturally have a lot of meat on them that are very
bony. So maybe that's an area that it is talking about natural.
תניא כארבעה מינייהו, tanya k'arba minaihu, now so those are the different
opinions. תניא כארבעה מינייהו tanya k'arba minaihu we have a ברייתא braisa
that teaches like four of the different positions earlier. Let's read the
ברייתא, braisa, תניא כארבעה מינייהו, tanya k'arba minaihu, רבי אומר בבית אחד
יאכל ועצם לא תשברו בו על הכשר הוא חייב al hakasher hu
chayav ואינו חייב על הפסול. ve'eino chayav al hapasul. Okay, so it's
interesting, רבי before who said about being fit to be eaten, here
says about being כשר not פסול which explains why the גמרא before
said that רבי holds of both positions. Either one exempts you and
he's only being more lenient. היתה לו שעת הכושר haysa lo shas
hakosher ונפסל בשעת אכילה venifsal beshas achilah let's say it was fit
and now became invalid and now became טמא, אין בו משום שבירת
עצם ein bo mishum sheviras etzem you go by right now and
therefore it does not have the problem of breaking the bones. So
there you see רבי the idea that רבי's position would exempt you
if right now it's not fit to be eaten. יש בו שיעור
אכילה, yesh bo shiur achilah,
יש בו משום שבירת עצם yesh bo mishum sheviras etzem if there's
enough meat to be eaten, it is the prohibition.
אין בו שיעור אכילה, ein bo shiur achilah, אין בו משום שבירת
עצם ein bo mishum sheviras etzem it's not. So that's the idea
that ראוי לאכילה means you need that amount of meat on it.
הראוי למזבח haraoy l'mizbeach אין בו משום שבירת עצם ein bo mishum
sheviras etzem if it's something that's going on the altar like the
fat tail does not have the prohibition. בשעת אכילה beshas achilah יש
בו משום שבירת עצם, שלא בשעת אכילה shelo beshas achilah אין בו
משום שבירת עצם and here's the other crazy קולא that on the
14th you don't have the prohibition. Okay, so there you have the
debate and let's just read one more line. איתמר, itamar, אבר שיש
עליו כזית בשר במקום זה eiver sheyesh alav kzayis basar bemakom zeh
ויש עליו כזית בשר במקום אחר. veyesh alav kzayis basar bemakom acher.
Exactly the same we discussed before. It has a כזית kzayis of
meat on it but not at the place of being broken. So
before we were debating whether what רבי would hold, here we're going
to see it's a debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan
ve'Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar יש בו משום שבירת
עצם you still have the prohibition. וריש לקיש אמר ve'Reish Lakish amar
אין בו משום שבירת עצם you don't. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש
eisivei Rabbi Yochanan le'Reish Lakish ועצם לא תשברו בו, don't break a
bone in it. אחד עצם שיש עליו כזית בשר echad etzem sheyesh
alav kzayis basar ואחד עצם שאין עליו כזית בשר ve'echad etzem she'ein
alav kzayis basar whether it has meat or not. מאי אין עליו
כזית בשר? mai ein alav kzayis basar? What does it mean you
transgress without meat? אילימא דאין עליו כזית בשר כלל eileima d'ein alav
kzayis basar klal if you mean literally no meat, which is I
think we would have said sure, why not? But no, here the
גמרא's assuming אמאי? amai? How could anybody say you transgress if there's
no meat on the bone? אמאי יש בו משום שבירת עצם? amai
yesh bo mishum sheviras etzem? How could that be? It has to
be some type of a thing that is in the context of
being eaten. So nobody would say if there's no meat on the
bone. אלא לאו הכי קאמר, ela lav hachi ka'amar, here's what it
means. אחד עצם שיש עליו כזית בשר במקום זה echad etzem sheyesh
alav kzayis basar bemakom zeh ואחד שאין עליו כזית בשר במקום זה
ויש עליו כזית בשר במקום אחר. ve'echad she'ein alav kzayis basar bemakom
zeh veyesh alav kzayis basar bemakom acher. Must mean like I said
that even if it doesn't have it exactly at the place where
you're breaking it, you still transgress.
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said לא, no. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
here's what it means.
אחד
עצם שיש עליו כזית בשר מבחוץ echad etzem sheyesh alav kzayis basar
mibachutz ואחד עצם שאין עליו כזית בשר מבחוץ ויש עליו כזית בשר
מבפנים ve'echad etzem she'ein alav kzayis basar mibachutz veyesh alav kzayis basar
mibifnim במקום שבירה. bemakom shevirah. It means you have to have a
כזית בשר kzayis basar but going back to Michael's point, it doesn't
have to be on the outside, it could be on the inside,
it could be the marrow. But he says I need there to
be a כזית kzayis and not only a כזית, kzayis, a כזית
kzayis at the place where it's being broken. What I will admit
is that the כזית kzayis can be on the inside. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says even if the כזית kzayis is lower in the
limb, you still transgress. Okay, and we will continue with this fun
discussion of breaking bones tomorrow.
Okay, bye.